# Diheng Zhang, M.A.

Phone: (917) 861-0223

dihengzhang@email.arizona.edu Email:

Linkedin:Diheng(Adam) Zhang

#### **Research Interests**

- Cognitive biases/deficits in mood and anxiety disorders and related neural mechanisms
- Bio/behavioral markers of mood and anxiety disorders
- Computational modeling of brain functions/dysfunctions and predicting symptom/markers

### **Summary of Professional Experience**

Graduate Assistant Aug. 2018 - Present

Psychophysiology Lab, University of Arizona

Supervisor: John J.B. Allen, Ph.D.

Research Assistant

Project Coordinator *Jun.* 2015 – *Jul.* 2018

Program for Anxiety, Cognition, and Treatment (PACT) Lab, University of Virginia

Supervisor: Bethany Teachman, Ph.D.

Research projects dedicated to developing, evaluating and disseminating novel interventions for mood and anxiety disorders.

New York, NY Langone Medical Center, New York University & Bellevue Hospital Center

Supervisors: Isaac Robert Galatzer-Levy, Ph.D. & Uzma Samadani, M.D., Ph.D.

Research project for establishing for a neural model for predicting early stage brain trauma.

Research Assistant: Summer Intern *Jun.* 2013 – Aug. 2013

CEDAR Clinic, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center

Supervisor: Kristen Woodberry, M.S.W., Ph.D.

Research project for understanding the prodromal phrase of early onset schizophrenia.

Research Assistant: Summer Intern

Department of Psychology, Harvard University

Supervisors: Jill Hooley, D.Phil. & Kenneth Allen, Ph.D. Research project for underpinning relationship between cognitive deficits and Non Suicidal Self Injury.

Intern Sept. 2013 - May 2014

Personalized Recover-Orientated Services (PROS) Program, Hamilton Madison House

Supervisor: Angela Yeung, Psy. D.

New York, NY

#### Education

#### Ph.D. Student in Clinical Psychology, University of Arizona

Tucson, AZ

Tucson, AZ

Boston, MA

Charlottesville, VA

*Jan.* 2013 – *Jun.* 2014

May 2013 - Aug. 2013

Cambridge, MA

School of Mind, Brain, and Behavior

Aug. 2018 - Present

M.A. Clinical Psychology, Columbia University in the City of New York

New York, NY

Teachers College, GPA: 3.84/4.00

Aug. 2012 - May 2014

B.Sc. Applied Psychology, Nanjing University

Nanjing, China

School of Social and Behavioral Science, GPA: 3.80/4.00

Sep. 2009 - Jul. 2012

#### **Presentations**

- **Zhang, D.,** Shi, Y., Wang, H. & Teachman, B.A. (2017, November). *Predictors of Attrition in a Public Online Interpretation Training Program for Anxiety.* Poster presented at Association for Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies' 2017 convention in San Diego, CA.
- Werntz, A.J., **Zhang, D.**, Geyer, E. & Teachman, B. A. (2017, November). *Am I anxious?: Implicit and explicit self-concepts of anxiety predict symptom acknowledgement*. Poster presented at Association for Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies' 2017 convention in San Diego, CA.
- Calicho-Mamani, C., **Zhang, D.**, Blaisdell, K.N., Friedmann, C.I., Werntz, A.J.& Teachman, B.A. (2017, November). *Gender and Age Differences in Social Media Advertising Reception: Using Facebook to Promote Free, Web-Based Interventions.* Poster presented at Diversifying Scholarship at UVA Interdisciplinary Conference in Charlottesville, VA.
- Calicho-Mamani, C., **Zhang, D.**, & Teachman, B.A. (2017, August). *Responding and Flexibility: Relationship between Variability on Interpretation Bias Measures and Anxiety and Depressive Symptoms.* Poster presented at University of Virginia Summer Research Symposium in Charlottesville, VA.
- Bacon, G., Teachman, B.A., **Zhang, D.** (2017, August). *The Impact of Education Level on Drinking Identity.* Poster presented at University of Virginia Summer Research Symposium in Charlottesville, VA.
- Matsuba, M., **Zhang, D.**, Graham, A., Hong, J., Dorfman, M. & Chen, X. (2014, August). *Analysis of Universal and Culture-Specific Negative Coping in Chinese Immigrants with Schizophrenia*. Poster presented at American Psychological Association's 2014 convention in Washington, D.C..
- **Zhang, D.**, Luguya, C., Chhuon, R., Wang, L. & Matsuba, M. (2013, August). *'Excessive Thinking' as a Cultural Idiom Used by Chinese to Explain Relatives' Psychiatric Etiology.* Poster presented at American Psychological Association's 2013 convention in Honolulu, HI.
- **Zhang, D.** (2012, November). *Chinese Adolescence Depression and Identity Formation*. Poster presented at International Education Week at Teachers College, Columbia University, New York, NY.

# Manuscripts and Publications

- Chow, P.I., Portnow, S., **Zhang, D.**, Salemink, E., Wiers, R.W., & Teachman, B.A. (2018). Comorbid Interpretation and Expectancy Bias in Social Anxiety and Alcohol Use. *Anxiety, Stress, and Coping*
- **Zhang, D.**, Shi, Y., Wang, H. & Teachman, B.A. (in prep). Predictors of Attrition in a Public Online Interpretation Training Program for Anxiety.
- Ji. L. J., Baee, S., **Zhang**, **D.**, Meyers, J., Funk, D., Portnow, S., Barnes, L., & Teachman, B. (Submitted). Multisession online interpretation bias training for anxiety in a community sample.
- Steinman, S.A., Portnow, S., Billingsley, A., **Zhang**, **D.**, & Teachman, B.A. (in prep). The presence of threat bias, but not the absence of positive bias, predicts trait and state anxiety in a large online sample
- Geng, L., Zhang, L., & **Zhang, D.** (2011). Improving spatial abilities through mindfulness: Effects on the mental rotation task. *Consciousness and Cognition*, 20(3), 801 806. doi: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.concog.2011.02.004

### **Honors and Awards**

GPSC Travel Grants, University of Arizona, Graduate & Professional Student Council (GPSC) Summer 2019

Departmental Scholarship, University of Arizona, Dept. of Psychology

Spring 2019

Flexibility Fund Awards, Academy of Psychological Clinical Science

Dec. 2018

Graduate Student Fellowship, University of Arizona, Dept. of Psychology

Aug. 2018 - Present

### Research Experience

Graduate Assistant Aug. 2018 – Present

Psychophysiology Lab, **University of Arizona** Supervisors: John J.B. Allen, Ph.D.

Tucson, AZ

• Under training of psychophysiology research methods and data analysis techniques, including EEG signal preprocessing and alpha power asymmetry analysis.

Project Coordinator Jun. 2015 – Jul. 2018

Program for Anxiety, Cognition, and Treatment (PACT) Lab, **University of Virginia** Supervisor: Bethany Teachman, Ph.D.

Charlottesville, VA

- Developed and managed the MindTrails Project, an online platform for testing and delivering novel Cognitive Bias Modification (CBM) interventions for anxiety disorders, with a reach over 2,500 participants.
- Developed programs and packages in Python and R to automatize data management, data cleaning, and analyses for multiple research studies to ensure data integrity and streamlining data preparation. (See **Github**).
- Recruited participants, analyzed research data and facilitated grant writings for multiple grant applications which resulted in a R01 grant.
- Programmed and managed online studies with Project Implicit and Amazon Mechanical Turk to assist graduate students' research projects.
- Recruited, trained and supervised research assistants for daily lab tasks, including participant recruitment, data management, data cleaning, and programming.
- Administrated study IRBs, dataset codebooks, experiment documentations, and lab supplies to enable smooth lab functioning.

Other collaborative projects at UVA:

- Extended the current computational model of the hippocampus, to achieve a higher level of temporal resolution in simulation with Matlab/C++, with Professor William Levy.
- Applied machine learning (ML) algorithms on MindTrails datasets for multiple research topics, including users' dropout prediction and subgroup classification, with Professor Hongning Wang.
- Modeled participants' mood fluctuations with datasets from an ecological momentary assessment (EMA) study to predict optimized-timing for intervention, with Professor Laura Barnes' group.
- Programmed fMRI studies with PsychoPy to facilitate lab transition from Matlab to Python, with Professor James Coan.

Research Assistant Jan. 2013 – Jun. 2014

Langone Medical Center, New York University & Bellevue Hospital Center

New York, NY

Supervisors: Isaac Robert Galatzer-Levy, Ph.D. & Uzma Samadani, M.D., Ph.D.

Research project for establishing model to predict PTSD in early stage.

- Assessed concussion or other trauma patients in emergency room (ER) to recruit eligible participants for research.
- Operated Eye-tracker to collect research data.
- Reviewed literature and collected trauma-related scales to facilitate experimental design.
- Administered data and case management including data entry, updating research logs, tracking new patients from patient regulation system and arranging further research appointment to assist project operation.

Research Assistant: Summer Intern

*Jun.* 2013 – Aug. 2013

Boston, MA

CEDAR Clinic, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center

Supervisor: Kristen Woodberry, M.S.W., Ph.D.

Research project for understanding prodromal phrase of early onset schizophrenia.

• Setup EEG, biofeedback equipments and experiment environment for study data collection.

- Assessed clients with SIPS to recruit participants for research study.
- Organized interview toolkits and salivation and blood collecting kits to support study recruitment.
- Reviewed research articles and feedbacks from reviewers to assist grant application.
- Established online surveys to collect feedback about research outcome to help design future researches.
- Applied administrative tasks including case management, case follow up and data management to support center daily running.

Research Assistant: Summer Intern

May 2013 - Aug. 2013

Department of Psychology, Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Supervisors: Jill Hooley, D.Phil. & Kenneth Allen, Ph.D.

Research project for underpinning relationship between cognitive deficits and Non Suicidal Self Injury.

- Operated portable EEG, delivered assessment (WAIS, etc.) and cognitive tests (Iowa Gambling Test, etc.) to collect experimental data.
- Scored questionnaires with Excel to establish dataset, calculated first-step research outcome and helped generate preliminary conclusion for research project.
- Coded case subjective responses to PANAS questions, discussed and proposed new ideas based on collected data to extend research project with further hypothesis.
- Conducted literature review on neuroimaging researches with fMRI targeting Default Mode Network to facilitate proposal writing.
- Organized case files, entered and cleaned up data to help with data management, storage and prepare for later analysis.

Research Assistant Oct. 2012 – May 2014

Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in the City of New York

New York, NY

Supervisor: Lawrence H. Yang, Ph.D.

Research group for investigating stereotypes towards schizophrenia consumers among Chinese immigrants.

- Translated research interviews whose battery included a wide array of tests with Chinese immigrants with psychosis and their family caregivers to prepare for further analysis.
- Coded, and trained lab members to code interview materials according to various coding schemes with Atlas.TI, to extend original stigma model to culture specific immigrant population in U.S..
- Prepared and submitted poster and symposium proposals to national conferences including APA, AAPA, and Teachers College Winter Roundtable to share research outcome. (See **Presentations** for more detail.)

### Clinical Experience

Intern
Hamilton Madison House

*Sept.* 2013 – *May* 2014

New York, NY

Supervisor: Angela Yeung, Psy. D.

Personalized Recover-Orientated Services (PROS) Program

- Designed and co-led multiple training groups to assist participants who experiencing Schizophrenia or Schizoaffective disorders to ameliorate their cognitive function and prepare them for returning to the community.
- Facilitated annual assessment for participants, and updated cases and documentation to assist daily operations
- Shadowed core staffs and sat in multiple skills-enhancement groups to gain clinical experience as a trainee.

Counselor, Senior Trainee

Feb. 2010 – Jul. 2012

Nanjing, China

Department of Psychology, Nanjing University

Supervisor: Karen Gabe, M.S.

Peer Counseling Program

- Delivered psychological counseling to students to assist them in handling academic pressure, major life events, and romantic relationships.
- Provided psychological supervision and facilitated evaluations of entry-level counselors to develop their skills and inspire personal growth.
- Initiated supporting group for sophomores to facilitate identity exploration, and to enhance their problem solving and stress-coping skills.
- Organized and facilitated Self Management And Recovery Training(SMART) groups to help students eliminate addictive behaviors including excessive gaming and smoking.
- Managed documents to support program operations.

#### Suicide Prevention Program

- Monitored Nanjing Yangtze River Bridge area weekly for potential suicidal behaviors and applied first-aid intervention to rescue suicide attempters.
- Assessed rescued individuals and offered psychological services to prevent later suicidal attempts.
- Created and managed website providing scientific information to raise public awareness on suicide and depression.

Psychiatry Intern

Department of Medical Psychotherapy, Nanjing Brain Hospital

Supervisor: Ning Zhang, M.D.

Oct. 2011 – Nov. 2011

Nanjing, China

- Managed and updated daily case files to support psychiatrists in following up with clients experiencing schizophrenia, depression and others psychiatry disorders.
- Interviewed incoming patients and performed initial assessment to facilitate diagnostic processes.
- Attended ward rounds under professional supervision to accumulate clinical experience and enhance understanding of diverse psychological disorders.

# Teaching/Mentoring Experience

Conference Attendance

| Teaching Assistant PSY 352: Personality PSY 150A: Structure of Mind & Behavior  | Aug. 2018 - Present<br>Spring 2019<br>Fall 2018  |
|---|--|
| Workshops<br>Delivered: Data Management and Analysis with R - a Five Sessions Bootcamp  | Summer 2017  |
| Mentoring Undergraduate Research Assistant Maryam Farooqui, B.S., University of Virginia Class of 2017 Kaitlin Wray, B.S., University of Virginia Class of 2017 Kellyn Blaisdell, B.S., Princeton University Class of 2016 Casey Michelle Baker, University of Virginia Class of 2018 Claudia Patricia Calicho-Mamani, University of Virginia Class of 2018 Imani Nichols, B.S., University of Virginia Class of 2017 | Aug. 2017 - May 2018<br>Aug. 2017 - May 2018<br>Aug. 2017 - May 2018<br>Jun. 2017 - May 2018<br>Jun. 2017 - May 2018<br>Sep. 2016 - May 2018 |
| Graduate Research Assistant<br>Anyi Zhang, M. Eng, Graduate School of Engineering, University of Virginia   | Jan Jun. 2017  |

Association for Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies' 2017 convention in San Diego, CA Association for Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies' 2016 convention in New York, NY

5

Nov. 2017

Oct. 2016

| Social & Affective Neuroscience Society Annual Meeting 2016 in New York, NY        | Apr. 2016 |
|--|-----------|
| Association for Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies' 2015 convention in Chicago, IL | Nov. 2015 |
| Social & Affective Neuroscience Society Annual Meeting 2015 in Boston, MA          | Apr. 2015 |
| American Psychological Association's 2014 convention in Washington, D.C.           | Aug. 2014 |
| Depression Among Asian Americans Conference in Edison, NJ                          | Apr. 2013 |
| The 30th Annual Teachers College Winter Roundtable Conference in New York, NY      | Feb. 2013 |

### **Professional Associations**

| Member, Association for Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies                            | Oct. 2015 – Oct. 2018              |
|---|------------------------------------|
| Member, The Social and Affective Neuroscience Society                                 | Apr. 2015 – Apr. 2017              |
| Member, Psi Chi National Honor Society in Psychology                                  | <i>Mar.</i> 2013 – <i>May</i> 2014 |
| Vice President, International Students' Psychology Association at Columbia University | Aug. 2013 – May 2014               |

### **Professional Skills**

**Experienced Working Environment:** Mac OS, MS Windows & Linux

Programming Languages: Python, R, SQL, Matlab, JavaScript/HTML/CSS & LATEX (use daily); Java (Web De-

velopment and Machine Learning); C/C++(learned in class); LISP (for fun)

Professional Softwares: SPSS, M-Plus, Atlas.TI & E-Prime

Online Service Package: Amazon Mechanical Turk, Qualtrics & Surveymonkey

# References Available Upon Request